Interest rates everyone thought were
going to go a lot higher. Oil prices,
they started to become a major problem.
And even though the S&P 500 ended up
gaining 20% that year, more companies in
1999 ended up going down than had gone
up. There are a lot of similarities
between now and 1999, and one of the
biggest ones is how far company
management teams will go to make sure
they're not one of the ones on the
outside looking in. And in 2026, that
means
a lot of them are lying to you,
especially about AI and what AI truly
means in terms of macroeconomy, the AI
bubble, stock prices, and a whole bunch
more.
When you hear about the market in 1999,
you'll immediately recognize more than
just superficial comparisons and general
themes. It isn't just bubble behavior
that we're talking about, either. There
is There's something more fundamental at
work. Going beyond what share prices are
doing to figure out what they actually
mean, and how what they actually mean
plays a role in a lot of things,
including future share prices. The truth
of the matter is neither you nor I have
any clue when or even if the stock
market's going to turn around. There's
simply no way to know. It's the very
definition of unpredictable, which is
why no one ever predicts it. And anyone
who does, they're just get lucky once,
and they never do it again. So right
now, there is, as you probably know, the
Iran war euphoria, how this thing is
going to be over with, plus the AI
bubble is back. It's FOMO times 11. This
is nothing new. FOMO was a huge part of
'99, although we didn't call it that
back then. But the AI bubble, it's not
all it appears to be, and I'm not really
talking about the technology itself, nor
necessarily its adoption. And what
better represents the spirit of the
market and the times than something
they're calling AI washing? Now this is
just company management teams lying to
you about what they're doing to make
sure that they're going to participate
in the bubble, just like they once did
back in 1999. But it's it's not just
unethical, it leads to all sorts of
confusing signs and signals with
distortions that ripple throughout the
marketplace as well as the real economy.
And as we know only too well, beyond.
Yes, I'm talking about Blue Owl Private
Credit, all that kind of stuff. There is
a lot going on here starting with the
bubble behavior lying.
Like I said, this is not strictly about
stock prices. It's about how chasing
them creates these distortions which go
far beyond the New York Exchange. So,
let let's start here. Let's see if this
sounds familiar. It comes from the New
York Times. Quote, "When they were hot,
they were very, very hot. But, when they
were not, they were losers. The story of
the stock market in 1999 was of stocks
that flew higher than at any time in the
last decade. Enough of them soared that
the major market indexes all closed the
year at record highs." And that's
understating it tremendously. The
best-performing stocks leaped not by
hundreds but by thousands of percentage
points. And applying that standard, it
was the year of the decade. And yet, all
that prosperity hid some weaknesses.
With interest rates rising and oil
prices soaring, many stocks struggled.
The Standard & Poor's index of 500
stocks gained 19 and 1/2% during the
year, but more issues in the index fell
than rose. And so, it does it sounds
familiar, but this is not a review of
2025 or necessarily a direct comparison.
While it was written on January 3rd,
2000 looking back at the historic year
of 1999,
as the author pointed out the Nasdaq it
had soared by an unprecedented 85.6%.
Yet even then, it hid some pretty big
losers including a lot of financial
firms. Again, this should sound very
familiar. As does the chase for anything
tech. At the time, it was the it was the
name of the bubble itself. Anything
dot-com was huge. Go back to New York
Times once more.
The size of the moves made by winners
reflects the speculative fever gripping
the market and is based on hopes that as
the internet transforms the economy,
companies that did not exist a few years
ago will become giants. In all that, the
example of Yahoo, one of the first of
the internet companies to go public,
stands out as the shining example. It
more than doubled the day it went
public, which was April 15th, 1996.
Within a few months, it fallen back to
the offering price, but an investor who
put $1,000 into the stock at the close
of trading that first day and held on
would now have a stock worth $80,500.
I almost never do ads, and I say no to
the vast majority of those that are
brought to my attention, but I was
thrilled to be able to work with today's
video sponsor, Monetary Metals. And the
reason is because they're solving a big
problem, one that I've been highlighting
for a very long period of time. Gold is
a safe haven, but other than sitting in
a vault, it doesn't do anything.
Monetary Metals fixes that. They let you
earn real yield paid in physical gold
without giving up ownership. It's not a
fund, it's not a paper claim, it's your
gold working for you. Every month, more
gold gets deposited into your account.
It's simple, it's transparent, and it is
fully insured. If you believe in gold as
a long-term store of value as I do, this
changes everything. Go to
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
That's monetary-metals.com/snyder
for all the details. We absolutely thank
them for being the sponsor of today's
video, and now let's get back to it.
Now, Yahoo would start to collapse
within months of the article's
publication, and it never regained its
early 2000 peak before Verizon bought
the struggling internet afterthought in
2017. Sure, people made money on Yahoo,
but it didn't live up to the peak hype
nor the valuations. And just as
importantly, the economy didn't keep
going on forever, either, as it would
struggle in 2000 before falling into the
dot com recession in 2001. With a whole
quote new economy that everyone talked
about in the late 90s and they kept
hyping it up year after year after year,
it eventually did live up to the hype to
a certain extent and it would take
decades and really several new
inventions that no one had even dreamed
of back then before it really could.
Primarily the smartphone. That's where
really e-commerce got unlocked. But
while the current stock market isn't
directly comparable, you know what they
say about how history rhymes,
particularly when markets get top-heavy
and stay that way. And what happens to
behavior during these periods when the
fun just seems like it's never going to
end and that there is no ceiling to any
of it.
Right now the stock market is reliving
its April 2025 where it took the
escalator down and the elevator back up.
This That reverses the old adage. They
used to say all the old um stock market
veterans, they used to say stocks they
take the escalator up climbing that
mythical wall of worry which never
existed by the way. They climb the
mythical wall of worry and then every
once in a while terrifying they they
take the elevator down.
Fueled by a combination of AI mania,
that's the dot com comparison, and in
the short run the euphoria over the Iran
conflict and how it's going to be over
tomorrow, it's pure FOMO right now, fear
of missing out. With momentum on
everyone's side so the ride upward can
take I mean who the hell knows how long.
Like Stephen and I were talking about in
yesterday's video on the oil side of the
current shock, you have to tip your cap
to President Trump. Whatever you think
of the president, he's absolutely
managed the futures price of oil and the
stock market brilliantly. Whenever the
former creeps up toward $100 and the
latter starts to wobble, out pops a
truth social or media statement saying
this thing is done. It'll be wrapped up
tomorrow or in the next couple days. And
then oil drops at least in the futures
market as we pointed out and stocks pop.
They keep going forever higher. But
where it gets tricky is the unsteady
foundation just like there had been in
1999. No one wants to be the turd in the
punch bowl, not when there's so much
money to be made. But, like the New York
Times review pointed out, there are
problems here, and they sound very
familiar, not the least of which are oil
prices themselves. And, as Stephen I
pointed out yesterday, what's really
happening in petroleum isn't what you
see in WTI futures. It's what you're
starting to see more clearly in
wholesale gasoline and increasingly at
the retail pump. That's not the only
challenge, of course, as I'll get into
with the job market, one area which is
nothing like 1999. But, with all that in
mind, you can understand why companies
might not want to be completely
truthful. They want to participate in
the stock market, but they don't want to
be too honest about why they're doing
what it is they're doing, this AI
washing that I brought up. Companies
wired with They've decided they would
rather lie to you to hope that they can
be part of the 1999 recreation here in
2026. Meanwhile, what's really going on
and the signals that you get something
else entirely.
Like I always say, you know it's not
good when central bankers start making
sense. That's really what rate cuts are.
They aren't stimulus. They're instead
officials admitting, "Hey, the economy
we told you was strong and resilient,
maybe even inflationary. Well, it turns
out it was none of those things. So,
we're going to start cutting our policy
rates, chasing the bond market, because
we're going to tell you that lower rates
are stimulus when they never really
are." Once you see the Pringles can in
J. Powell or Christine Lagarde's hands,
they're telling you they now see that
things are getting serious in the
downside in the real economy. Rate cuts
are confirmation of growing trouble that
even central bankers can see it, too.
It's the same, to an extent, whenever
officials talk about markets. Last year,
for example, even before we got the
cockroaches, there'd been a flurry of
reports from various official and
quasi-public institutions like the BIS,
warning everybody about private credit.
Now, we've got officials looking at the
stock market and saying, "What the
It's not unlike 1999." Quote, "A senior
Bank of England official warned that
high asset prices didn't reflect the
level of risk in the markets, suggesting
that global markets could fall." Who
would ever say such a thing? Sarah
Breeden, the the British central bank's
deputy governor for financial stability,
said that current share prices weren't
yet consistent with the scale of
economic pressures facing markets.
Breeden made her remarks in an interview
with the BBC as the war on Iran
approached the start of its third month
with the Strait of Hormuz remaining
largely closed to trade. "There's been a
lot of risk out there and yet asset
prices are at all-time highs," Breeden
said. "We expect that there will be an
adjustment at some point." Now, the
deputy governor said the thing that
keeps her awake at night was the
likelihood of multiple economic risks
hitting simultaneously.
A major macroeconomic shock, confidence
in private credit goes, AI and other
risky valuations readjust. What happens
in that environment? And are we prepared
for it? Now, this isn't to say 2026 is
the top in the market or that the bust
will be dot-com all over again. It's
more so that the rise in '99 didn't
reflect what everyone thought it had.
Part of the problem is putting all
equities together in a single index. The
index does well, but only because part
of it does. So, what does that really
tell us? What does that really mean? Is
it like Sarah Breeden is suggesting
maybe things are not as robust as they
otherwise appear. Now, in 1999, it meant
everyone wanted new. They wanted the
they wanted a dot-com web name kind of a
thingy. Banks, industrial firms, the old
economy, who cared about that? The new
stuff was up 86%.
The dot-com boom was supposed to be the
roaring '90s, taking new tech and then
roaring long-term into the forever
future. While the hype eventually paid
off, it was on much narrower grounds
than everyone had hoped. And it turned
out there were a lot of other factors,
eurodollar, that mattered a whole lot
more than just the status of e-commerce
moving forward. Stocks only reflect when
stockholders are buying and by how much.
That's it. Same as it was in 1999 really
as tech names it seemed like they had no
ceiling, but for everyone else it didn't
matter until the tech mania actually
died out. And while this dynamic is in
play, understandably human nature,
everybody's going to do whatever they
possibly can to make sure that they're a
big part of it up to and including
pushing the boundaries, pushing the
envelope, maybe going a little bit too
far and straying across the line. There
is a ton of unethical behavior that goes
along with bubbles, which is one reason
why bubbles end up being such big
distortions. It's We're talking about as
as far as information what share prices
are supposed to be, which they never
really are. But if so many share prices
did reflect something fundamental
under bubble valuations and bubble
bubble periods
it's more distortion than anything else.
I mean, there's huge money to be made
and so no one wants to be left behind.
The bubble's always fun on the way up
and you really do never have an idea
when the party's going to end. You've
got zero clue. No one knew that 2000 was
going to be the top and even after it
showed up, there were rallies later in
the year which looked like the market
might overcome what was many people
considered just another short-run period
of weakness climbing that wall of worry
and that it would head even higher by
2001 at the latest. You really don't
know ahead of time. You can't possibly
know ahead of time. That's what makes
this such a tricky proposition. How can
you know what constitutes too narrow and
too far for the Nasdaq or AI or the
ability to just ignore oil? The biggest
thing is overlooking everything else,
getting tunnel vision. What matters is
only the bubble, the next record high
and for individual stocks, too. And that
brings us to something they're calling
AI washing. Blaming artificial
intelligence for what are nothing more
than regular bad economy layoffs.
Businesses have been cutting back on
workers more and more and case you
hadn't noticed the evidence for Dr.
Beverage pretty much everywhere outside
the New York Stock Exchange, but rather
than admit they over hired and business
is underwhelming because the economy
really does suck and J. Powell was
really wrong, unlike in 1999 by the way,
management teams, they are outright
lying about what they're doing and why.
Now, why they're doing it is easy. CEOs
think the only way they can stay on the
1999 path is to keep shareholders happy.
And how do you do that when business is
poor?
Well, you lay off workers and then tell
the stock market you're not reacting to
a bad economy you didn't see coming. No,
no, no, no. You're proactively cutting
down on payrolls to become lean and more
profitable, ready to tackle AI and put
it to efficient, profitable use right
away. And this is exactly what Jack
Dorsey's Block did not that long ago,
just a couple of weeks ago. Though with
a huge difference. The former Twitter
CEO didn't lie about anything. Dorsey
was honest. He said they got in the
recovery wrong thinking there would be
one, so they over hired. And then not
needing nearly as many people with the
economy in the toilet, if there ever was
an upturn, they wanted to be ready to
take advantage of it, so then maybe
Block would use AI to help the business
do so if or when it ever showed up. But
all the media heard was AI and layoffs
and put the two together and it was off
to the races with a sexy story. Another
very common occurrence that we saw in
1999. Take something turning into
something else consistent with the stock
euphoria and boom, stock prices reflect
the euphoria, not the actual truth. As
far as Block is concerned, the stock
soared and it has stayed up. So you can
already see the incentive to try to play
the narrative. As I said, companies are
just outright lying about what's going
on with them and their workers. Quote,
"In February, OpenAI CEO Sam Altman
admitted at the India AI Impact Summit
that companies are AI-washing layoffs,
blaming artificial intelligence for
workforce reductions they would have
made anyway. Yes, even the man selling
the technology says some of this is
fiction. A lot of it is fiction. In
fact, the vast majority is fiction.
A resume.org survey of a thousand hiring
managers found that 59%
say they emphasize AI's role in layoffs
because it is, quote, viewed more
favorably by stakeholders than saying
layoffs or hiring freezes are driven by
financial constraints. Only 9% say that
AI had fully replaced any role. This is
not a technology story. It's a
management honesty story that happens to
involve technology. Sounds a lot like
1999 there as well. The reason it works
is well understood. Decades of research
on how markets react to layoff
announcements have established a
consistent pattern. Investors punish
companies that frame cuts as a response
to problems. But when a company frames
the same cuts as proactive
restructuring, the penalty disappears.
The stated reason for the layoff matters
that more than the fact of the layoff.
AI has become the most powerful
proactive frame available. We're
restructuring around AI as a growth
signal, at least that's the how the
stock market takes it. We over-hired
during the pandemic and revenue softened
is an accountability signal, trying to
get back on track with forgot how to
grow. So, from the stock market
perspective, you think you're getting an
AI revolution that's already being put
in place, and then high share prices
confirm that. But what's really
happening is layoffs are validating
forgot how to grow or remember how to
fire. All the while, AI really doesn't
have much to do with it apart from
covering it all up under the latest
narrative machine. And that's your
comparison to 1999.
Narratives, bubbles are nothing if not
narrative. And the farther they go and
the faster they get there, the more
people want to believe in it, even if it
is, like here with AI washing, a
complete and total lie. That's taking it
too far. It's not a complete and total
lie, but there's enough lying to go
around and this is quite consistent with
all of it. Just like 1999, there's tons
of hype and most of it ended up being
for nothing. Sure, there was a future
way down the road, but the vast majority
was just bad signals including hiding or
at least obscuring some of the cracks
which began to show up even in the
vaunted 1990s booming economy,
legitimately booming economy that looks
nothing like what we have today. For the
stock market, there's the risk it could
reverse. Though again, your guess is as
good as mine about when that could
happen and what it what it might mean if
it actually does. For the economy,
there's this constant dissonance. Shares
are soaring, therefore we're told
everything must be fine. So, it's the
labor market setbacks which are being
over hyped. It's completely backward and
in reality, it's companies lying and
using AI hype to cover up the real
economic story and all the related
financial consequences which go along
with them. In 1999,
those were the tech boom and the IPOs
and everything else which set the stage
for the prolonged bust and recession
which followed. In 2026,
it's private credit and shadow banking.
And the truth is, bubbles don't
represent reality, they distort it and
the biggest ones naturally twist
everything around them the most. So, we
have CEOs lying about layoffs due to a
bad economy trying to turn them into AI
pointing to some future positive economy
that doesn't actually exist, at least
not right now. There's your comparison
to the 1999.
Everything that you thought was
happening isn't actually happening. And
so, this isn't really about AI at all or
even stock market stock prices, stock
indexes, or stocks in one sense or
another. It's about behavior and
distortions of behavior and then
ultimately
the consequences that come from it.
And of course, one of the biggest
consequences will be coming from private
credit. When we talk about private
credit crisis, people think you mean the
next Lehman Brothers when it's not
really about a Lehman Brothers because
there won't be a Lehman Brothers and the
real story, it's all in the video link
below. As always, thank you very much
for joining me. Huge thank you Euro
Dollar University members and
subscribers and until next time,
take care.